Guide to the Gertrude Folks Zimand and Savel Zimand Papers, 1911-1958
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Gertrude Folks Zimand and Savel Zimand Papers
1911-1958
Zimand, Gertrude Folks, 1894-1966
Zimand, Savel, 1891-
0.6 cubic feet (3 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The Zimand papers primarily concern Gertrude Folks Zimand's work in France during World War I with the American Committee for Devastated France. There is additional biographical materials as well as items relating to her father, Homer Folks, Zimand's publications, and her work with the National Child Labor Committee. There is also a significant collection of material relating to Savel Zimand's work as a writer and journalist.
Biographical Note
Gertrude Folks Zimand (1894-1966) was born in New York City and graduated from Vassar College in 1916. As an undergraduate she was head of the Suffrage Club and the Socialist Club; she was also active in the Settlement Association and the debating society. After graduation Gertrude Folks became a field investigator for the National Child Labor Committee, an organization which her father, Homer Folks, had helped found in 1904. When her Vassar classmates selected her for the Borden Memorial Fund Prize for a year of travel, she decided to use the money to work in France. After a brief stint with the American Red Cross she returned to work with the National Child Labor Committee, devoting the rest of her life to the problems of child labor. She wrote extensively on that subject, publishing several books and editing the committee’s magazine American Child. Gertrude Folks Zimand served as both general secretary and a trustee of the National Child Labor Committee and was a founder of its National Committee on Employment of Youth. She was married in 1926 to Savel Zimand, a writer and correspondent for several newspapers including the New York Times and New York Evening Post. As one of the foremost campaigners against child labor abuses, she fought for an eight-hour work day for children and for a law to keep children in school until the age of fourteen. She also fought for a constitutional amendment outlawing child labor.
Savel Zimand (1891-1967)was born in Rumania. He came to the United States in 1913. He was a writer, educator and advocate for public health and economic reform. His work took him around the world and introduced him to luminaries in the arts, sciences and politics.
Scope and Content Note
The Zimand papers primarily concern Gertrude Folks Zimand's work in France during World War I with the American Committee for Devastated France and include a diary for 1917, letters written to her family, 1917-1919, and photographs. Other items include a tribute to her father, Homer Folks, Zimand's publications, the 1911 Yonkers High School yearbook, letters received on her retirement from the National Child Labor Committee, 1955, an inventory of her papers at the Social Welfare History Archives Center, University of Minnesota, and biographical material.
There is also material relating to Savel Zimand's work as a journalist. Correspondents include the painter, Jack B. Yeats; poet George Russell (AE); historian and supporter of Irish independence, Alice Green; Mizra Ismail, the Diwan of Mysore (now Karnataka, India); biologist and sociologist, Patrick Geddes; Irish labor leader and politician, Robert Smillie; and a variety of other political, cultural and social figures.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Additional publications of Gertrude Folks Zimand are cataloged in the
Vassar College Alumnae/i Collection.
Subject Headings
Names:
Folks, Homer, 1867-1963; Geddes, Patrick, Sir, 1854-1932; Green, Alice Stopford, 1848-1929; Ismail, Mirza M., Sir, 1883-; Russell, George William, 1867-1935; Smillie, Robert, 1857-1940; Yeats, Jack Butler, 1871-1957; Folks family
Organizations:
American Committee for Devastated France; Yonkers High School (Yonkers, N.Y.); National Child Labor Committee (U.S.); University of Minnesota. Social Welfare History Archives Center
Subjects:
World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--War work; Women--Diaries; War--Women's work; International relief--France; Children--Employment; Journalists
Children--Employment
Places:
United States--Social conditions; France--Description and travel
Document Types:
Diaries; Photographs
VCL Categories
Children and Children's Literature; Journalism; War and War Crimes
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, July 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Savel Zimand.
Series List
- Series I. Gertrude Folks Zimand, (Boxes 1-3)
- Series II. Savel Zimand, (Boxes 2-3, Multiple Collections, Box 8)
Container List
- Gertrude Folks Zimand
  - Lists of items in the collection. (Folder 1.1)
  - Information about Gertrude Folks Zimand’s honors and tributes. (Folder 1.2)
  - Inventory of G.F.Z. Papers deposited in the Social Welfare History Archives Center, University of Minnesota Libraries. (Folder 1.3)
  - Diary, while in France, 14 July - 4 Oct 1917 (Folder 1.4)
  - Summary of diary dated 23 August 1917, and extract from a diary "while with the American Commission to Devastated France at Blerancourt, Department of the Aisne, during the German offensive of March 1918,", 1917-1918 (Folder 1.5)
  - Letters to a family from France, and typescripts, 1917-1918 (Folder 1.6-7)
  - Blerancourt photographs. (Folder 1.8)
  - Letters from Homer Folks, Gertrude’s father, to the family, from France, ca. 1919 (Folder 1.9)
  - Retirement as General Secretary of Natioanal Child Labor Committee, 1955; (photostats) (Folder 2.1)
  - Publications (Folder 2.2)
  - Tributes to Homer Folks, 1937, 1959 (Folder 2.3)
  - Thirty Years of Service: A Tribute to Homer Folks, 1923 (Box 3)
  - Gertrude Folks Zimand: A Tribute, 1967; (3 copies) (Box 3)
  - Yonkers High School Yearbook, 1911 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous biographical material (Folder 3.1)
  - Correspondence with Burgess Johnson, 1953; (photocopies) (Folder 3.2)
  - Photographs and news clippings re Gertrude and Savel Zimand (Folder 2.4)
- Savel Zimand
  - Russell, George (AE), 1921-1930 (Folder 2.5)
  - Green, Alice, 1921-1923, n.d. (Folder 2.6)
  - Ireland — Yeats, Jack B., 6 Sep 1921 (Folder 2.7)
  - Ireland — Williams, R.V., 13 Dec 1921 (Folder 2.7)
  - Ireland — Gallagher, Paddy, 14 Dec 1921 (Folder 2.7)
  - Ireland — Skeffington, Hanna F. Sheehy, 28 Sep 1921 (Folder 2.7)
  - Ireland — Childers, Molly (Mrs Robert Erskine Childers), 16 Nov 1921 (Folder 2.7)
  - Trotsky, Leon — interview, 1923 (Folder 2.8)
  - Soviet Union — paper rubles (Folder 2.9)
  - India — Andrews, C.F. (Charles Freer), 9 June 1925, 3 Apr 1924 (Folder 2.10)
  - India — Ghandi, Devadas, 14 Feb 1924 (Folder 2.10)
  - India — Transcript of interview with Mahatma Ghandi (Folder 2.10)
  - England — Cole, G.D.H (George Douglas Howard), 23 June 1921 (Folder 2.11)
  - England — Greendwood, Arthur, 1 June 1923 (Folder 2.11)
  - England — Tawney, R. H., 1920-1921 (Folder 2.11)
  - England — Middleton, J.S., 1920-1930 (Folder 2.11)
  - England — Webb, Sydney and Beatrice, 1921 - 1922 (Folder 2.11)
  - Responses from world political leaders re: world peace — includes Lord Robert Cecil, Gustav Stresemann, Constantine Rakovsky, Austen Chamberlain, Michael Hainisch and Leon Blum (Folder 2.12)
  - La Fontaine, Henri-Marie, 25 Mar and 10 Jan 1920 (Folder 2.13)
  - Geddes, Patrick, 1923-1924 (Folder 2.14)
  - Smillie, Robert, 1920-1925 (Folder 2.15)
  - Gompers, Samuel, 23 Dec 1921 (Folder 2.16)
  - Nevinson, Henry W., 24 Dec 1921 (Folder 2.16)
  - Autographed photographs of Leon Trotsky, Madame Lenin and Mikhail Ivanovich Kalinin, 1922 (Folder 2.17)
  - Ismail, Mizra, 1924-1958 (Folder 2.18)
  - Khan, Zulfiqar Ali, 24 Feb 1924 (Folder 2.19)
  - Calvert, H., 15 Feb [1924] (Folder 2.19)
  - Chintamani, C.Y., 26 Mar 1924 (Folder 2.19)
  - Darling, Malcolm, 25 Feb [1924] (Folder 2.19)
  - Douglas, James G, 12 Oct 1921 (Folder 2.20)
  - Henry, Paul, 18 Aug 1921 (Folder 2.20)
  - Henry, Paul and Grace, 7 Jan 1924 (Folder 2.20)
  - Henry R.M., 8 Oct 1921 (Folder 2.20)
  - Marshall, John, 12 Mar 1924 (Folder 2.21)
  - Plunkett, Horace, 9 Sep 1921 (Folder 2.21)
  - Sastri, Srinivasa, 13 and 25 Mar 1924 (Folder 2.21)
  - Living India, by Savel Zimand, dedicated to G.F.Z. (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Anatoly Lunacharsky, Commissar for Education of the Soviet Union (Multiple Collections — Box 8)